<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Giving Jar Blog</title>
    <atom:link href="http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <link>http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/</link>
    <description>Discover Giving Jar, Nonprofits, and Charitable Giving</description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 20:35:56 +0000</pubDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>Charity Spotlight: Helping Women Period</title>
        <link>http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/charity-spotlight-helping-women-period/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/charity-spotlight-helping-women-period/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.helpingwomenperiod.org/&quot; title=&quot;Helping Women Period Homepage&quot;&gt;Helping Women Period&lt;/a&gt; wants to remove the barriers of self-sufficiency that many homeless and low income women face daily. They provide feminine hygiene products such as sanitary pads and tampons to women in and around Lansing, Michigan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this charity spotlight, I spoke with the Founders of Helping Women Period, Amy Stephenson and Lysne Tait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;origin-story&quot;&gt;Origin Story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early in 2015, Amy and Lysne both read that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fns.usda.gov/wic/women-infants-and-children-wic&quot; title=&quot;Women, Infant, and Children Program&quot;&gt;WIC&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fns.usda.gov/snap/outreach/states/michigan.htm&quot; title=&quot;Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program of Michigan&quot;&gt;SNAP&lt;/a&gt; (food stamps) cannot be used to purchase sanitary pads and tampons. They were shocked that such a basic need was not supported by state and federal aid programs. This was also a matter of dignity. Homeless and low-income women without running water had no way to take care of basic feminine hygiene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two friends decided to organize a fundraiser. They hoped to raise $500 to help provide women in need with feminine hygiene products. Their small fundraiser blew up when it was announced on Facebook, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly facing over 100 attendees, Amy and Lysne had to find a new venue. With so much support, they also decided to start a nonprofit. Within five days they had gone from fundraiser to founding Helping Women Period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spotlight/helping-women-period/product-baskets.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;today&quot;&gt;Today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helping Women Period now provides feminine hygiene products to charities in the tri-county area for distribution. They have a great partnership with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.michco.com/&quot; title=&quot;MichCo Homepage&quot;&gt;MichCo&lt;/a&gt; that allows them to purchase products at the best price, and they hold regular fundraising events and product drives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to pads and tampons, Helping Women Period provides handmade bags that allow products to be carried discretely. They also have donation boxes at various businesses in Lansing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;big-wins&quot;&gt;Big Wins&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their first year, Helping Women Period raised $14,000 and donated $8,000 worth of products. Considering the original fundraiser had a goal of $500, providing this much aid to women was a major victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also partnered with several local charities to help distribute the products they acquire. These partnerships will continue to be vital to the growth of Helping Women Period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spotlight/helping-women-period/product-drive.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;to-nonprofits&quot;&gt;To Nonprofits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are starting a charity, start something you believe in and make sure it is needed. Be organized from the very beginning and be accountable for your work. Leverage your strengths, collaborate with others to leverage theirs, and take care of your volunteers. Make it fun for them and thank them when they’re done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goals&quot;&gt;Goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going into their second year, Amy and Lysne are confident that Helping Women Period can raise $20,000. This would be an extraordinary 40% increase over their first year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are also working on a handbook that would open up a Helping Women Period affiliate program. These affiliations would be a great way to provide aid to women in cities beyond Lansing. Long-term, Amy and Lysne would also like to help women in other countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spotlight/helping-women-period/amy-and-lysne.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;to-donors&quot;&gt;To Donors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like a charity’s cause, reach out to them! Try volunteering. Charities really appreciate volunteers and they will take care of you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way you can reach out is to ask your employer about sponsoring a charity. A business sponsorship is a big deal for many charities. Sometimes it’s as easy as starting a conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;get-involved&quot;&gt;Get Involved&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.helpingwomenperiod.org/&quot; title=&quot;Helping Women Period Homepage&quot;&gt;Helping Women Period&lt;/a&gt;, you can reach them by clicking one of the buttons below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list-inline text-center web-links&quot;&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://www.helpingwomenperiod.org/&quot; title=&quot;Homepage&quot; class=&quot;home&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;fa-stack fa-lg&quot;&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-circle fa-stack-2x&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-home fa-stack-1x fa-inverse&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;


    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/helpingwomenperiod&quot; title=&quot;Facebook&quot; class=&quot;facebook&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;fa-stack fa-lg&quot;&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-circle fa-stack-2x&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-facebook fa-stack-1x fa-inverse&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;


    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/HelpingWomen1&quot; title=&quot;Twitter&quot; class=&quot;twitter&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;fa-stack fa-lg&quot;&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-circle fa-stack-2x&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-twitter fa-stack-1x fa-inverse&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;


&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;photographs-courtesy-of-helping-women-period2&quot;&gt;Photographs courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/helpingwomenperiod/&quot; title=&quot;Helping Women Period on Facebook&quot;&gt;Helping Women Period&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h6&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Charity Spotlight: Creating Heroes Stephen&#39;s Way</title>
        <link>http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/charity-spotlight-creating-heroes-stephens-way/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/charity-spotlight-creating-heroes-stephens-way/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://creatingheroesstephensway.com/&quot; title=&quot;Creating Heroes Stephen&#39;s Way Homepage&quot;&gt;Creating Heroes Stephen’s Way&lt;/a&gt; is a comic book shop in Lansing, Michigan that provides kids with a safe place to play games, learn to read and draw from comics, and get mentoring from enthusiastic volunteers. All profits from their comic book sales are dedicated to helping children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this charity spotlight, I spoke with the Director of Creating Heroes Stephen’s Way, Monica Jahner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;origin-story&quot;&gt;Origin Story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monica’s brother, Stephen, used to run Capital City Collectibles, a comic book and hobby game shop in Lansing, Michigan. When he passed away in 2010, the business was left in Monica’s hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After learning about all of the work Stephen had been doing to help children in the area, she decided to carry on his philanthropic efforts. She made the decision official by reinventing Capital City Collectibles as the charity, Creating Heroes Stephen’s Way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spotlight/creating-heroes-stephens-way/wonder-woman-iron-man.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Cosplay and the Iron Man Helmet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;today&quot;&gt;Today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating Heroes Stephen’s Way continues to sell comic books at the back of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/EverybodyReads&quot; title=&quot;Everybody Reads Book Store&quot;&gt;Everybody Reads Book Store&lt;/a&gt;. All profits go to mentoring and other youth programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These programs include literacy through comic books and drawing lessons through &lt;em&gt;Rick &amp;amp; Joe’s Comics Crash Course for Kids&lt;/em&gt;. Creating Heroes Stephen’s Way also offers children a safe place to play games such as &lt;em&gt;Magic: The Gathering&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pokemon&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;HeroClix&lt;/em&gt;. Regular tournaments are also a big hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating Heroes Stephen’s Way also participates in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.freecomicbookday.com/&quot; title=&quot;Free Comic Book Day&quot;&gt;Free Comic Book Day&lt;/a&gt;, encourages kids to get involved in cosplay, and they even got one of Robert Downey Jr.’s Iron Man costumes for one of their events!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;big-wins&quot;&gt;Big Wins&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each child she is able to help is a big win for Monica, but it’s also not uncommon that she is able to help the parents through her work at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://nwlansing.org/about/&quot; title=&quot;NorthWest Initiative of Lansing&quot;&gt;NorthWest Initiative&lt;/a&gt;. The NorthWest Initiative is a nonprofit dedicated to helping build and sustain healthy communities in Lansing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Monica meets new children, sometimes she also discovers parents who need help getting back on their feet. If she can help those parents get the right experience, education, and licensing to get back into the workforce, she can help a whole family. Those wins are huge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spotlight/creating-heroes-stephens-way/creating-dc-fans-stephens-way.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Creating DC Fans Stephen&#39;s Way&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;to-nonprofits&quot;&gt;To Nonprofits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to start a nonprofit or charity, consider the misery you have experienced in your life. “Make that your mission and save someone from the pain you’ve experienced.” Monica also advises that nonprofits are not the place to make a lot of money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goals&quot;&gt;Goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kids are always looking for love and family. Monica would like to find more opportunities to bring kids together and keep them engaged. Expanding the literacy program, introducing new subjects, and tutoring are great ways to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating Heroes Stephen’s Way regularly holds &lt;em&gt;Magic: The Gathering&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pokemon&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;HeroClix&lt;/em&gt; tournaments, but they would also like to include more volunteers to help with other games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spotlight/creating-heroes-stephens-way/kids-and-clix.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Kids, Comics, and HeroClix&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;to-donors&quot;&gt;To Donors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monica has this advice to give to donors: “Run with your passions. Put yourself out there and the energy will come back to you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find something you love to do and do it for a good cause. Do you like drawing, reading comics, or playing games? Creating Heroes Stephen’s Way is looking for volunteers like you. Share those interests with children. You’ll change lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;get-involved&quot;&gt;Get Involved&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about &lt;a href=&quot;http://creatingheroesstephensway.com/&quot; title=&quot;Creating Heroes Stephen&#39;s Way Homepage&quot;&gt;Creating Heroes Stephen’s Way&lt;/a&gt;, you can reach them by clicking one of the buttons below or visiting them at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/EverybodyReads&quot; title=&quot;Everybody Reads Book Store&quot;&gt;Everybody Reads&lt;/a&gt; in Lansing, Michigan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list-inline text-center web-links&quot;&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://creatingheroesstephensway.com/&quot; title=&quot;Homepage&quot; class=&quot;home&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;fa-stack fa-lg&quot;&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-circle fa-stack-2x&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-home fa-stack-1x fa-inverse&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;


    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/Creating-Heroes-Stephens-Way-327694434004028&quot; title=&quot;Facebook&quot; class=&quot;facebook&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;fa-stack fa-lg&quot;&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-circle fa-stack-2x&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-facebook fa-stack-1x fa-inverse&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;



&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;photographs-courtesy-of-creating-heroes-stephens-way2&quot;&gt;Photographs courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/Creating-Heroes-Stephens-Way-327694434004028/&quot; title=&quot;Creating Heroes Stephen&#39;s Way on Facebook&quot;&gt;Creating Heroes Stephen’s Way&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h6&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Improvements in Interviewland</title>
        <link>http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/progress-report-4-improvements-in-interviewland/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/progress-report-4-improvements-in-interviewland/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; Progress reports will be trimmed back for a while to assess the importance of the extra details in the original reports. If you want those details back, ask for them in an email or on social media.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress reports are Giving Jar’s way of celebrating &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#success&quot; title=&quot;Success Section&quot;&gt;Success&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, reflecting on &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#failure&quot; title=&quot;Failure Section&quot;&gt;Failure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (and what was learned from it), giving &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#thanks&quot; title=&quot;Thanks Section&quot;&gt;Thanks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and taking a peek at what’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#upcoming&quot; title=&quot;Upcoming Section&quot;&gt;Up and Coming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Hopefully you will find these progress reports informative. As always, all &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#104;&amp;#101;&amp;#108;&amp;#108;&amp;#111;&amp;#064;&amp;#103;&amp;#105;&amp;#118;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#103;&amp;#106;&amp;#097;&amp;#114;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot; title=&quot;Email Giving Jar&quot;&gt;feedback&lt;/a&gt; is welcome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;success&quot;&gt;Success&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the major wins in this progress report:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.givingjar.org/charity-spotlight-cuts-and-convos/&quot; title=&quot;Charity Spotlight: Cuts and Convos&quot;&gt;Cuts and Convos&lt;/a&gt; was spotlighted.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interviewed two amazing charities!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Started Giving Jar business formation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attended Rotary Club meeting as a guest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;failure&quot;&gt;Failure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are almost always setbacks when working on a project of any size. Here are the lessons learned from the last round of setbacks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scheduling blog posts on a static site is a headache!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Local charity news gets more attention than national news.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Need to spend more time learning about marketing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thanks&quot;&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to Jonathan Arias of &lt;a href=&quot;http://cutsandconvos.com&quot; title=&quot;Cuts and Convos Homepage&quot;&gt;Cuts and Convos&lt;/a&gt;. The conversations are always great with this guy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you, Monica, for the impromptu interview for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.creatingheroesstephensway.com/&quot; title=&quot;Creating Heroes Stephen&#39;s Way Homepage&quot;&gt;Creating Heroes Stephen’s Way&lt;/a&gt; last week!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amy and Lysne also took the time to meet and give an interview for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.helpingwomenperiod.org/&quot; title=&quot;Helping Women Period Homepage&quot;&gt;Helping Women Period&lt;/a&gt;. Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;16 mailing list members (-0)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14 Twitter followers (+2)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;39 Facebook page likes (+5)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;upcoming&quot;&gt;Upcoming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s where the focus will be in the next two weeks at Giving Jar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Writing the next two charity spotlights.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Revising the social media strategy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Filing paperwork for business formation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automatic blog post scheduling.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enumerate minimal viable product ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, Giving Jar is looking for charities to interview. If you know a charity that might be interested, &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#104;&amp;#101;&amp;#108;&amp;#108;&amp;#111;&amp;#064;&amp;#103;&amp;#105;&amp;#118;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#103;&amp;#106;&amp;#097;&amp;#114;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot; title=&quot;Email Giving Jar&quot;&gt;send an email&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/givingjar&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar on Twitter&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt;, or write on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/givingjarorg&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar on Facebook&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; wall.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Charity Spotlight: Cuts and Convos</title>
        <link>http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/charity-spotlight-cuts-and-convos/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/charity-spotlight-cuts-and-convos/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cutsandconvos.com&quot; title=&quot;Cuts and Convos Homepage&quot;&gt;Cuts and Convos&lt;/a&gt; helps low-income residents of Michigan look good, feel good, and ultimately become gainfully employed. The charity accomplishes this through complimentary haircuts and beauty services with uplifting conversations. They know that a fresh look and improved outlook on life may be the key to turning someone’s life around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this charity spotlight I spoke with the President of Cuts and Convos, Jonathan Arias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spotlight/cuts-and-convos/cuts-and-convos-kids-too.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Cuts and Convos Helps Kids Too&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;origin-story&quot;&gt;Origin Story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cuts and Convos grew out of Jonathan’s desire to help others. When he lived in Tallahassee, he got no satisfaction from his job so he volunteered for a community charity event and was encouraged to cut hair. Despite being tentative about cutting a stranger’s hair, he accepted the challenge. In Jonathan’s words, “life is about what you give.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experience was so fulfilling that Jonathan decided he wanted to continue cutting hair. The next opportunity to do so presented itself when he moved to Lansing, Michigan. He had some extra bandwidth, so he offered his services to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lcrm.org/&quot; title=&quot;Lansing City Rescue Mission Homepage&quot;&gt;City Rescue Mission of Lansing&lt;/a&gt;. Cuts and Convos was started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;today&quot;&gt;Today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cuts and Convos wants to help people become gainfully employed by helping them look good (which in turn helps them feel good) and empower them with encouraging and directed conversations. They have helped over 250 Michigan residents and recently celebrated their one year anniversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are able to connect with so many people by working with other charitable organizations in the area such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.homelessangels.org/&quot; title=&quot;Homeless Angels&quot;&gt;Homeless Angels&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.havenhouseel.org/&quot; title=&quot;Haven House&quot;&gt;Haven House&lt;/a&gt;. They also maintain a strong relationship with the City Rescue Mission of Lansing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spotlight/cuts-and-convos/cuts-and-convos-before-after.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Before and After Cut and Convo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;big-wins&quot;&gt;Big Wins&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cuts and Convos has won the &lt;a href=&quot;http://soupgrantlansing.com/&quot; title=&quot;Soup Grant Lansing Homepage&quot;&gt;Soup Grant Lansing&lt;/a&gt; micro-grant twice and they recently introduced a free van service to help get interested persons to church, but for Jonathan the big wins are the personal stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such story was about a man who was in prison for 21 years and had just been released three days prior. His hair had not been cut in seven years and he was eager for a fresh start. Jonathan wasn’t just cutting a man’s hair that day, he was cutting his past away and helping him move forward with a new life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan loves helping people make those kinds of transformations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;advice-to-nonprofits&quot;&gt;Advice to Nonprofits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For anyone who is running a nonprofit or is interested in starting a charity, Jonathan recommends focusing on your mission and goals. It’s all about the good work you’re doing. Love your work and word will get around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spotlight/cuts-and-convos/cuts-and-convos-hair-styling.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Cuts and Convos Styles Hair&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goals&quot;&gt;Goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cuts and Convos would love to expand to more locations. Doing this would require bringing in more donations, hair care supplies, and equipment, but it would also mean touching more lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan also wants to expand on the impact of “cuts and conversation” by starting a podcast or vlog. He would cut the hair of an expert in a field such as teen pregnancy or sexually transmitted diseases and help spread awareness of those topics through the conversation that ensues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;advice-for-donors&quot;&gt;Advice For Donors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in donating to a charity, look at the work the charity is doing and see how your donations will be used. Commit your charitable efforts toward something you love and consider volunteering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;get-involved&quot;&gt;Get Involved&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about Cuts and Convos, you can reach them by clicking one of the buttons below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list-inline text-center web-links&quot;&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://cutsandconvos.com&quot; title=&quot;Homepage&quot; class=&quot;home&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;fa-stack fa-lg&quot;&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-circle fa-stack-2x&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-home fa-stack-1x fa-inverse&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;


    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/cutsandconvos&quot; title=&quot;Facebook&quot; class=&quot;facebook&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;fa-stack fa-lg&quot;&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-circle fa-stack-2x&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-facebook fa-stack-1x fa-inverse&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;


    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cutsandconvos&quot; title=&quot;Twitter&quot; class=&quot;twitter&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;fa-stack fa-lg&quot;&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-circle fa-stack-2x&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-twitter fa-stack-1x fa-inverse&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;


&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;photographs-courtesy-of-cuts-and-convos1-with-consent-from-subjects&quot;&gt;Photographs courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://cutsandconvos.com&quot; title=&quot;Cuts and Convos Homepage&quot;&gt;Cuts and Convos&lt;/a&gt; with consent from subjects.&lt;/h6&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Getting Ahead on Spotlights</title>
        <link>http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/progress-report-3-getting-ahead-on-spotlights/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/progress-report-3-getting-ahead-on-spotlights/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Progress reports are Giving Jar’s way of celebrating &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#success&quot; title=&quot;Success Section&quot;&gt;Success&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, reflecting on &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#failure&quot; title=&quot;Failure Section&quot;&gt;Failure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (and what was learned from it), giving &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#thanks&quot; title=&quot;Thanks Section&quot;&gt;Thanks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and taking a peek at what’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#upcoming&quot; title=&quot;Upcoming Section&quot;&gt;Up and Coming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Hopefully you will find these progress reports informative. If you have feedback to offer, &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#104;&amp;#101;&amp;#108;&amp;#108;&amp;#111;&amp;#064;&amp;#103;&amp;#105;&amp;#118;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#103;&amp;#106;&amp;#097;&amp;#114;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot; title=&quot;Email Giving Jar&quot;&gt;send it along&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;success&quot;&gt;Success&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the major wins in this progress report:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The second charity spotlight was published.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Various minor website improvements were made.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interviewed the third charity, in record time!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Met with accountant and made some hard decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t want to know about the details of these wins, feel free to skip to &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#failure&quot; title=&quot;Failure Section&quot;&gt;Failure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;charity-spotlight-2&quot;&gt;Charity Spotlight #2&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.givingjar.org/charity-spotlight-michigan-remembers-9-11/&quot; title=&quot;Charity Spotlight: Michigan Remembers 9/11&quot;&gt;second charity spotlight&lt;/a&gt; was published, and already there are many improvements being made to the process. The interview itself took about the same amount of time, but the steps to go from interview to written article took about 4-5 hours less than they did after the first charity interview!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every other week, Giving Jar will interview a different charity and write about the amazing and good things they are doing. The second spotlight covered &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.michiganremembers.dreamhosters.com/&quot; title=&quot;Michigan Remembers 9/11 Homepage&quot;&gt;Michigan Remembers 9/11&lt;/a&gt;, a charity that helps newer generations remember the significance of September 11, 2001 and honor first responders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;website-improvements&quot;&gt;Website Improvements&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Updating the Giving Jar websites is a very manual process right now. The goal is to fully automate publishing progress reports, charity spotlights, and all other content. Small strides were made these past two weeks: the blog is now using Jekyll 3 instead of GitHub Pages and is being built with Grunt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were some superficial changes made as well. The logo now has a colored background, the landing page has a new social card that doesn’t use the logo, and there’s a link in the top right of the blog to all of the published charity spotlights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;third-charity-interview&quot;&gt;Third Charity Interview&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slowly, but surely the charity interviews and spotlights are picking up steam. Getting ahead on the interviews will free up more time to work on the software platform, which is the next big step for Giving Jar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interview went about 33% faster and still covered all of the spotlight topics and the extra research Giving Jar is doing to learn about how charities operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;getting-numbers-in-order&quot;&gt;Getting Numbers in Order&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accountant meeting went well. Dale, at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.agpccpa.com/&quot; title=&quot;Abraham and Gaffney, P.C. Homepage&quot;&gt;Abraham and Gaffney, P.C.&lt;/a&gt;, is a great guy and very practical. The big topic was how Giving Jar should be organized as a business. Dale explained the options, what course of action would need to be taken when a decision is made, and how the business structure would need to change as Giving Jar grows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving Jar is going to be founded as an LLC. With only one employee, this will offer the best balance of business independence and simplicity in management. Hopefully the name “Giving Jar” will stick!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;failure&quot;&gt;Failure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are almost always setbacks when working on a project of any size. Here are the lessons learned from the last round of setbacks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cold-calling takes a lot of energy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yep! Only one major lesson learned this time, everything else went pretty smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the stories behind those takeaways. If you don’t want the details, jump ahead to the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#thanks&quot; title=&quot;Thanks Section&quot;&gt;Thanks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cold-calling-takes-energy&quot;&gt;Cold-Calling Takes Energy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an effort to get ahead on the charity interviews and spotlights, lots of cold calls were made to charities in the Lansing area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big spreadsheet was created to keep track of when and how various charities were contacted so as not to spam them. Only one charity responded, too, so more calls will need to be made, and other tactics will need to be tried in order to pick up the pace on interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thanks&quot;&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big thanks go to Scott Watkins of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.michiganremembers.dreamhosters.com/&quot; title=&quot;Michigan Remembers 9/11 Homepage&quot;&gt;Michigan Remembers 9/11&lt;/a&gt;. The interview was great and so was the referral to the local Rotary Club!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you, Jonathan Arias, for the help getting ahead on the next charity spotlight!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, thanks to everyone following Giving Jar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;16 mailing list members&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;12 Twitter followers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;34 Facebook page likes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;upcoming&quot;&gt;Upcoming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s where the focus will be in the next two weeks at Giving Jar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The next charity spotlight will be published!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More effort will be placed on contacting charities and building up a queue of spotlights.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An attorney will be contacted so Giving Jar can be established as an LLC.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hopefully there will be much more progress on automating deployments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, Giving Jar is looking for charities to interview. If you know a charity that might be interested, &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#104;&amp;#101;&amp;#108;&amp;#108;&amp;#111;&amp;#064;&amp;#103;&amp;#105;&amp;#118;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#103;&amp;#106;&amp;#097;&amp;#114;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot; title=&quot;Email Giving Jar&quot;&gt;send an email&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/givingjar&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar on Twitter&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt;, or write on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/givingjarorg&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar on Facebook&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; wall.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Charity Spotlight: Michigan Remembers 9/11</title>
        <link>http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/charity-spotlight-michigan-remembers-9-11/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/charity-spotlight-michigan-remembers-9-11/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.michiganremembers.dreamhosters.com/&quot; title=&quot;Michigan Remembers 9/11 Homepage&quot;&gt;Michigan Remembers 9/11&lt;/a&gt; wants to make sure the significance of the tragic events on September 11, 2001 lives on in the minds and hearts of Michiganders for generations to come. They know that high school graduates this year may not have any personal recollection of that day, though, and they are helping to educate our youth so that the tragedy of 9/11 will long be remembered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this charity spotlight I spoke with the Treasurer of Michigan Remembers 9/11, Scott Watkins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spotlight/michigan-remembers-9-11/2015-never-forget.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Never Forget Those Who Helped and Those Who Lived&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;origin-story&quot;&gt;Origin Story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On September 11, 2001, two of Scott’s colleagues, Patrick Anderson and Ilhan Geckil, were attending a conference at the World Trade Center when the first plane hit. Cell towers were completely jammed. Facebook and other means of getting immediate updates from family and friends did not exist. It took Patrick and Ilhan hours to get to away from the WTC buildings and use a land line to contact their family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scott’s friends survived this tragic day, but they will never forget the sight of first responders running to the catastrophe, not thinking they may lose their lives, just rushing to help save the lives of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scott and Patrick founded Michigan Remembers 9/11 in 2007 to honor those who lost and risked their lives on that tragic day. They also want to make sure that first responders everywhere are honored for the service and risks they take every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;today&quot;&gt;Today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michigan Remembers 9/11 has done extensive research to identify the people of Michigan who died or risked their lives on that tragic day and shared their stories on their &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.michiganremembers.dreamhosters.com/?page_id=213&quot; title=&quot;Michigan Remembers 9/11 - In Remembrance Page&quot;&gt;In Remembrance&lt;/a&gt; site. They also maintain an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.michiganremembers.dreamhosters.com/?page_id=665&quot; title=&quot;Michigan Remembers 9/11 - Interactive Map of Michigan 9/11 Memorials&quot;&gt;interactive map&lt;/a&gt; of 9/11 memorials in the state of Michigan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each year they award three scholarships to the winners of an essay contest that asks junior and senior high school students to reflect on how the events of September 11, 2001 have had an impact on their life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The charity also organizes an annual “Run to Remember.” This fundraiser is a 5K that reminds participants of the trek Stephen Siller made on foot with 60 pounds of gear, from the Brooklyn Battery Tunnel to the Twin Towers, before giving his life saving others. Donations for this event send two Michigan first responders to the “Tunnel to Tower” run in New York, further honoring those who risk their lives on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spotlight/michigan-remembers-9-11/2015-scholarship-essay-winners.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;2015 Scholarship Essay Winners&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;advice-to-nonprofits&quot;&gt;Advice to Nonprofits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scott’s advice for anyone wanting to start their own nonprofit is “Don’t be afraid to ask for help.” There are many lawyers and news stations that offer help nonprofits for little or no cost. All you have to do is reach out to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;big-wins&quot;&gt;Big Wins&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It required a great amount of time and effort to identify the people with Michigan connections who were directly impacted by 9/11. When this research was complete, they began sharing their stories, identifying memorials, and organizing events to honor their memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participation in the charity really started to grow when Michigan Remembers 9/11 introduced their annual scholarship and 5K. Organizing these events is challenging, but for Scott and his peers, helping younger generations remember that day while honoring those affected by 9/11 is rewarding and well worth the effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spotlight/michigan-remembers-9-11/2015-run-to-remember.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;2015 Run to Remember&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goals&quot;&gt;Goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The members of Michigan Remembers 9/11 want their remembrance and celebration to be engaging. They would love to see participation in their annual 5K to double or even triple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The charity would also like to become more active throughout the year as well. To do this, they would like to start a heroes recognition program that, each month, rewards first responders for doing something special in the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;advice-for-donors&quot;&gt;Advice For Donors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scott suggests donating to a cause that makes you feel good. Look to your local community and find opportunities where you can help. When you donate or volunteer locally, you have the best chance of seeing the results of your contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;get-involved&quot;&gt;Get Involved&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about Michigan Remembers 9/11, you can reach them using the links below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list-inline text-center web-links&quot;&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://www.michiganremembers.dreamhosters.com/&quot; title=&quot;Homepage&quot; class=&quot;home&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;fa-stack fa-lg&quot;&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-circle fa-stack-2x&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-home fa-stack-1x fa-inverse&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;


    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/michiganremembers&quot; title=&quot;Facebook&quot; class=&quot;facebook&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;fa-stack fa-lg&quot;&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-circle fa-stack-2x&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-facebook fa-stack-1x fa-inverse&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;


    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/miremembers911&quot; title=&quot;Twitter&quot; class=&quot;twitter&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;fa-stack fa-lg&quot;&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-circle fa-stack-2x&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-twitter fa-stack-1x fa-inverse&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;


&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;photographs-courtesy-of-michigan-remembers-9111&quot;&gt;Photographs Courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.michiganremembers.dreamhosters.com/&quot; title=&quot;Michigan Remembers 9/11 Homepage&quot;&gt;Michigan Remembers 9/11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Charity Spotlights Are a Go!</title>
        <link>http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/progress-report-2-spotlights-are-a-go/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/progress-report-2-spotlights-are-a-go/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Progress reports are Giving Jar’s way of celebrating &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#success&quot; title=&quot;Success Section&quot;&gt;Success&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, reflecting on &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#failure&quot; title=&quot;Failure Section&quot;&gt;Failure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (and what was learned from it), giving &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#thanks&quot; title=&quot;Thanks Section&quot;&gt;Thanks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and taking a peek at what’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#upcoming&quot; title=&quot;Upcoming Section&quot;&gt;Up and Coming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Hopefully you will find these progress reports informative. If you have feedback to offer, &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#104;&amp;#101;&amp;#108;&amp;#108;&amp;#111;&amp;#064;&amp;#103;&amp;#105;&amp;#118;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#103;&amp;#106;&amp;#097;&amp;#114;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot; title=&quot;Email Giving Jar&quot;&gt;send it along&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;success&quot;&gt;Success&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the major wins in this progress report:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first charity spotlight was published.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first progress report was sent out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wrote about the development of the landing page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t want to know about the details of these wins, feel free to skip to &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#failure&quot; title=&quot;Failure Section&quot;&gt;Failure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;charity-spotlights&quot;&gt;Charity Spotlights&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably the most exciting news to report is that the &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.givingjar.org/charity-spotlight-building-twentyone/&quot; title=&quot;Charity Spotlight: Building Twentyone&quot;&gt;first charity spotlight&lt;/a&gt; was published!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every other week, Giving Jar will interview a different charity and write about the amazing and good things they are doing. The first spotlight covered &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.buildingtwentyone.org/&quot; title=&quot;Building Twentyone Homepage&quot;&gt;Building Twentyone&lt;/a&gt;, a teen center with an indoor skate park located between Holt and Mason, Michigan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Giving Jar is located just outside Lansing, Michigan, expect many of the early spotlights to focus on mid-Michigan charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;progress-reports&quot;&gt;Progress Reports&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first progress report was sent out two weeks ago. It was pretty long because it covered about a month of work at Giving Jar. This and all future reports will cover two weeks of progress, so you’ll be reading much shorter reports moving forward. They’ll also be much easier and faster to write!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Version 1.0 of the progress report structure was also established. If you haven’t picked up on it yet, this structure is &lt;em&gt;SFTU&lt;/em&gt; (not to be confused with &lt;em&gt;STFU&lt;/em&gt;). A section to celebrate &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Success&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, a section to reflect on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Failure&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, a section to give &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, and a section to peek at &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Upcoming&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;whats-in-a-landing-page&quot;&gt;What’s in a Landing Page?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A long, technical &lt;a href=&quot;http://technicalrex.com/whats-in-a-landing-page/&quot; title=&quot;What&#39;s in a Landing Page? on Technical Rex&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; about what went into the Giving Jar landing page was written and published on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://technicalrex.com&quot; title=&quot;Technical Rex Homepage&quot;&gt;Technical Rex&lt;/a&gt; blog. If you’re making your own landing page you should read it thoroughly. There is a lot to think about!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;failure&quot;&gt;Failure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are almost always setbacks when working on a project of any size. Here are the lessons learned from the last round of setbacks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transcribing a voice recording takes time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Celebrate people, not just charities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the stories behind those takeaways. If you don’t want the details, jump ahead to the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#thanks&quot; title=&quot;Thanks Section&quot;&gt;Thanks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;transcribing-a-voice-recording-takes-time&quot;&gt;Transcribing a Voice Recording Takes Time&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of information was covered in the interview with Benjamin Schartow of Building Twentyone. Notes were taken, but they weren’t good enough to distill all of that information down into a 500-600 word article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transcribing the interview into &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/givingjar/filing-cabinet/blob/master/files/interviews/2015-12-18-building-twentyone.md&quot; title=&quot;Benjamin Schartow of Building Twentyone Interview&quot;&gt;text&lt;/a&gt; worked, but it took a loooooong time. Sixty-nine minutes of conversation took over 3 hours to transcribe!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that a nice format came out of it, and capturing that same information in future interviews should take much less time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;celebrate-people-not-just-charities&quot;&gt;Celebrate People, Not Just Charities&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a bit of a face palm moment. The Building Twentyone story started with tragedy, but out of it came an organization that is really working hard to help keep teens safe and set them up for better futures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The writing captures this, but the interview and photoshoot was scheduled at a time when teens were still in school. That meant no people in any of the pictures. :(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thanks&quot;&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big thanks go out to Benjamin Schartow at Building Twentyone not just for the interview, but for creating a wonderful teen center that helps empower teens and volunteers. You can follow Building Twentyone on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Building21&quot; title=&quot;Building Twentyone on Twitter&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/buildingtwentyone&quot; title=&quot;Building Twentyone on Facebook&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More thanks go out to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MrIanKast&quot; title=&quot;Ian Kast on Twitter&quot;&gt;Ian Kast&lt;/a&gt; for taking photos for Giving Jar on his day off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, thanks to everyone following Giving Jar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;13 mailing list members&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;10 Twitter followers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;28 Facebook page likes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;upcoming&quot;&gt;Upcoming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next charity spotlight will be published next week! As always, Giving Jar is looking for charities to interview. If you know a charity that might be interested, &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#104;&amp;#101;&amp;#108;&amp;#108;&amp;#111;&amp;#064;&amp;#103;&amp;#105;&amp;#118;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#103;&amp;#106;&amp;#097;&amp;#114;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot; title=&quot;Email Giving Jar&quot;&gt;send an email&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/givingjar&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar on Twitter&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt;, or write to Giving Jar on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/givingjarorg&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar on Facebook&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week that meeting with the accountant will happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, there are a number of efficiencies needed to speed up the turnaround time on progress reports and charity spotlights. Namely, automating the publishing process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t sound like much, but with two days off for New Years, it’s enough!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Charity Spotlight: Building Twentyone</title>
        <link>http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/charity-spotlight-building-twentyone/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/charity-spotlight-building-twentyone/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.buildingtwentyone.org/&quot; title=&quot;Building Twentyone Homepage&quot;&gt;Building Twentyone&lt;/a&gt; helps teenagers develop positive habits and values by giving them a safe, constructive place to drop in after school. They offer tutoring, a large space for safe party alternatives, workspaces for homework and projects, and the only indoor skate park within 75 miles of Lansing, Michigan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this charity spotlight I spoke with the Executive Director of Building Twentyone, Benjamin Schartow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spotlight/building-twentyone/skate-park.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Building Twentyone&#39;s Indoor Skate Park&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;origin-story&quot;&gt;Origin Story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About five years ago, tragedy rocked the Holt community. A group of seniors from Holt High School, who had been partying at MSU, crashed into a tree. Three of the seniors lost their lives. The driver had been drinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of the community met to discuss what could be done to change teen perceptions. This is when Benjamin knew he had to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Who is offering an alternative for these teenagers?” was the question Benjamin asked. When no one answered, he decided to take action. After talking with students, he began offering 5th Quarter parties after football games. These parties provided free pizza, a DJ, inflatables, giveaways, and a safe alternative to other house parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These 5th Quarter parties paved the way to Building Twentyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;today&quot;&gt;Today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building Twentyone’s campus consists of two large buildings between Mason and Holt. Students can be bussed there after school. There are a number of workshops offered, such as photography, DJ, and improv. Building Twentyone also offers tutoring, games, and plenty of space for personal projects. There is also a lake out back where students can boat and fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there’s the skate park. Benjamin says it wasn’t part of his original vision for Building Twentyone, but a couple of volunteers put their hearts and backs into it and made it happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empowering volunteers is something else Building Twentyone does well. Most of the staff are volunteers who don’t have leadership backgrounds. It’s not just teens who are looking for a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spotlight/building-twentyone/work-area.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;One of Building Twentyone&#39;s Many Open Workspaces&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;big-wins&quot;&gt;Big Wins&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been some big moments for Building Twentyone this year. They have started holding assemblies at Holt Junior High with uplifting messages. The teen center has also been around long enough to see the long-term positive impact it has on teenagers. Working with a teen for a year or more and watching their life completely turn around is a very personal accomplishment for Benjamin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building Twentyone also recently celebrated its largest fundraiser. With utility bills exceeding $900 in the winter, those donations help a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;advice-for-donors&quot;&gt;Advice For Donors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benjamin revealed to me that Building Twentyone is primarily volunteer-operated. The larger expenses are rent and utilities. It’s very easy for those expenses to exceed 33% of their expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When donors look at that percentage to gauge the quality of a charity, it’s also important that they look at the value being offered by that number. Facilities like Building Twentyone’s are invaluable to teens, and letting them explore technology, art, and other indoor activities year-round have a high energy cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, Building Twentyone was recently awarded a grant that will reduce their utility bills by 70%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spotlight/building-twentyone/graffiti-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;One Side-Effect of Massively Expensive Lights &quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goals&quot;&gt;Goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the near future, Benjamin would like to add digital media, speech writing, and public speaking workshops to their programming. He is also working with Mason schools to help influence more teens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking farther ahead, Benjamin thinks it would be great to see an additional Building Twentyone location in the Lansing area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;advice-to-nonprofits&quot;&gt;Advice to Nonprofits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For anyone running a charity, Benjamin suggests planning fundraisers well in advance. Pick a date and work backward on your calendar to decide when you should start promoting it. If you start too late, there may not be enough time to spread the word and attract enough donors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benjamin also recommends looking for volunteers who are capable in areas where you are weak. Keep people doing what they love for as long as they love it. Touch the lives of your volunteers and they will become champions of your cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spotlight/building-twentyone/building-sign.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Building Twentyone&#39;s Sign&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;get-involved&quot;&gt;Get Involved&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about Building Twentyone or get involved, you can find them at the links below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list-inline text-center web-links&quot;&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://www.buildingtwentyone.org&quot; title=&quot;Homepage&quot; class=&quot;home&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;fa-stack fa-lg&quot;&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-circle fa-stack-2x&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-home fa-stack-1x fa-inverse&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;


    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/buildingtwentyone&quot; title=&quot;Facebook&quot; class=&quot;facebook&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;fa-stack fa-lg&quot;&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-circle fa-stack-2x&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-facebook fa-stack-1x fa-inverse&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;


    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Building21&quot; title=&quot;Twitter&quot; class=&quot;twitter&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;fa-stack fa-lg&quot;&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-circle fa-stack-2x&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-twitter fa-stack-1x fa-inverse&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;


    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://instagram.com/buildingtwentyone&quot; title=&quot;Instagram&quot; class=&quot;instagram&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;fa-stack fa-lg&quot;&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-circle fa-stack-2x&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
                &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-instagram fa-stack-1x fa-inverse&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;photography-by-ian-kast2&quot;&gt;Photography by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MrIanKast&quot; title=&quot;Ian Kast on Twitter&quot;&gt;Ian Kast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 23 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Landing Page is Live!</title>
        <link>http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/progress-report-1-landing-page-is-live/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/progress-report-1-landing-page-is-live/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Progress reports are Giving Jar’s way of celebrating &lt;a href=&quot;#success&quot; title=&quot;Success Section&quot;&gt;success&lt;/a&gt;, reflecting on &lt;a href=&quot;#failure&quot; title=&quot;Failure Section&quot;&gt;failure&lt;/a&gt; (and what was learned from it), giving &lt;a href=&quot;#thanks&quot; title=&quot;Thanks Section&quot;&gt;thanks&lt;/a&gt;, and taking a peek at what’s &lt;a href=&quot;#upcoming&quot; title=&quot;Upcoming Section&quot;&gt;up and coming&lt;/a&gt;. Hopefully you will find these progress reports informative. If you have feedback to offer, send it along!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this is the first progress report, it’s not so much an update as it is a baseline from which all other progress reports can be measured. The next one will be much shorter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;success&quot;&gt;Success&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the major wins in this progress report:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The landing page was launched.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Giving Jar blog is available for consumption.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A weekly newsletter is in production.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Curated news with positive messages are shared daily.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The filing cabinet is open for all to peruse.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All browser-visible content has been open sourced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t want to know about the details of these wins, feel free to skip to &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#failure&quot; title=&quot;Failure Section&quot;&gt;Failure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;landing-page&quot;&gt;Landing Page&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest news of the first progress report is that the &lt;a href=&quot;http://givingjar.org&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar Landing Page&quot;&gt;landing page&lt;/a&gt; is live! Go there to learn all about Giving Jar and sign up for the newsletter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about what went into the landing page (logo design, wordsmithing, mobile-friendly layout, analytics, etc.), read &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://technicalrex.com/whats-in-a-landing-page/&quot; title=&quot;What&#39;s in a Landing Page? on the Technical Rex Blog&quot;&gt;What’s in a Landing Page?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://technicalrex.com&quot; title=&quot;Technical Rex Blog&quot;&gt;Technical Rex blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;giving-jar-blog&quot;&gt;Giving Jar Blog&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing is the earliest way that Giving Jar can help people discover charities and learn about the Giving Jar platform. The charity spotlights and progress reports are two such examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All written content will be published to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.givingjar.org&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar Blog&quot;&gt;Giving Jar blog&lt;/a&gt;. If the content is more technical in nature, you’ll find the details on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://technicalrex.com&quot; title=&quot;Technical Rex Blog&quot;&gt;Technical Rex blog&lt;/a&gt;. Until Giving Jar gets its own development blog, those technical articles will just be linked to from here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you prefer to get your news in one place, there are Atom feeds for both blogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;weekly-newsletter&quot;&gt;Weekly Newsletter&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of this writing, there is a sign up form on the Giving Jar landing page. Subscribe if you want to discover more about nonprofits, charitable giving, and Giving Jar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The newsletter will be sent weekly and will contain one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Charity Spotlights.&lt;/strong&gt; These charity interviews will help nonprofits get the word out about their mission and explore valuable information about how they operate, the challenges they face, and how donors can help.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Progress Reports.&lt;/strong&gt; This is what you’re reading now. These reports are how Giving Jar keep interested readers up to date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;curated-news&quot;&gt;Curated News&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idea was a last-minute addition to the rollout of the landing page. If you follow Giving Jar on social media then you will see daily items from the news about charities and donations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These shared links exist to inform and inspire. Each one is hand-picked because of the positive message or information it provides about the nonprofit space. They are not ads and Giving Jar does not make money from them whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;open-filing-cabinet&quot;&gt;Open Filing Cabinet&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the name of transparency and potentially helping other startups out, all files that don’t have sensitive&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; information will be made publicly available in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/givingjar/filing-cabinet&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar Filing Cabinet&quot;&gt;Giving Jar Filing Cabinet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now there are two files available:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/givingjar/filing-cabinet/blob/master/files/guides/blogging-guide.md&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar Blogging Guide&quot;&gt;Giving Jar Blogging Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/givingjar/filing-cabinet/blob/master/files/guides/social-media-guide.md&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar Social Media Guide&quot;&gt;Giving Jar Social Media Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;open-source-content&quot;&gt;Open Source Content&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the same vein as the open filing cabinet, all web content for Giving Jar is being open sourced. The following repositories are available for perusal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/givingjar/givingjar.org&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar Landing Page Code&quot;&gt;Giving Jar Landing Page Front-end&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/givingjar/blog.givingjar.org&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar Blog Code&quot;&gt;Giving Jar Blog (made with Jekyll)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/givingjar/media&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar Media Assets&quot;&gt;Giving Jar Media Assets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to fork and use these resources, but please abide by the license assigned to each repository. If there is no license file, then the content of the repository should not be used without explicit permission from Giving Jar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;failure&quot;&gt;Failure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are almost always setbacks when working on a project of any size. Here are the lessons learned from the last round of setbacks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tasks should be small and specific.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expect technical difficulties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the stories behind those takeaways. If you don’t want the details, jump ahead to the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#thanks&quot; title=&quot;Thanks Section&quot;&gt;Thanks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tasks-should-be-small-and-specific&quot;&gt;Tasks Should Be Small and Specific.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first handful of tasks for Giving Jar were very high-level:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create landing page.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create blog.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create newsletter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason these tasks should have been smaller is a matter of prioritization. Here’s a real example: hours of time went into picking a color scheme for the site. After the photos were taken, though, it was obvious what the color scheme should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;expect-technical-difficulties&quot;&gt;Expect Technical Difficulties.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technical difficulties will happen. When they do, it’s important to be able to quickly adapt your plan accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting up email for &lt;code&gt;givingjar.org&lt;/code&gt; went poorly because server issues were causing 2-5 hour delays in email delivery. If you are working on a remote system and run into issues, bring up their status page. It might save you hours if you quickly discover the issue is on their side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bonus Takeaway:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;If you offer a service to others, be very forthcoming on your website and social media when issues crop up!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acquiring an SSL certificate was also quite the rollercoaster ride. The gist of the lesson learned here is to hold off on purchasing software until you need it. Giving Jar doesn’t need an SSL certificate right now, but when it does, &lt;a href=&quot;https://letsencrypt.org&quot; title=&quot;Let&#39;s Encrypt SSL Certificates&quot;&gt;Let’s Encrypt&lt;/a&gt; will be the first stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thanks&quot;&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The landing page wouldn’t look nearly as good if it weren’t for photographic prowess of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MrIanKast&quot; title=&quot;Ian Kast on Twitter&quot;&gt;Ian Kast&lt;/a&gt;. Same goes for &lt;a href=&quot;http://deanattali.com/&quot; title=&quot;Dean Attali Homepage&quot;&gt;Dean Attali&lt;/a&gt;, creator of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://deanattali.com/beautiful-jekyll/&quot; title=&quot;Beautiful Jekyll Homepage&quot;&gt;Beautiful Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; theme that the Giving Jar blog is based on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will never be enough thanks to everyone building amazing free tools. &lt;a href=&quot;https://inkscape.org/&quot; title=&quot;Inkscape Homepage&quot;&gt;Inkscape&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gimp.org/&quot; title=&quot;GIMP Homepage&quot;&gt;GIMP&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://atom.io/&quot; title=&quot;Atom Homepage&quot;&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://slack.com/&quot; title=&quot;Slack Homepage&quot;&gt;Slack&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.git-scm.com/&quot; title=&quot;Git Homepage&quot;&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot; title=&quot;GitHub Homepage&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zoho.com/&quot; title=&quot;Zoho Homepage&quot;&gt;Zoho&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://surge.sh/&quot; title=&quot;Surge Homepage&quot;&gt;Surge&lt;/a&gt;, that’s you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tip of the hat to everyone who helped by giving feedback during the development process as well (Chris, Sam, Rich, Kevin, and everyone in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lansing.codes/&quot; title=&quot;Lansing Codes Homepage&quot;&gt;Lansing Codes&lt;/a&gt; Slack team). Never underestimate the value of someone who is willing to critique your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, thanks to everyone following Giving Jar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;12 mailing list members&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7 Twitter followers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;19 Facebook page likes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;upcoming&quot;&gt;Upcoming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first charity spotlight will be published next week! Giving Jar is on the lookout for charities to interview, too. If you know a charity that might be interested, &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#104;&amp;#101;&amp;#108;&amp;#108;&amp;#111;&amp;#064;&amp;#103;&amp;#105;&amp;#118;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#103;&amp;#106;&amp;#097;&amp;#114;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&quot; title=&quot;Email Giving Jar&quot;&gt;send an email&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/givingjar&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar on Twitter&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt;, or write on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/givingjarorg&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar on Facebook&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A meeting needs to be scheduled with an accountant. There are lots of financial considerations to be made for a startup as it rolls into the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t sound like much, but with Christmas falling at the end of the next week, it’ll be enough!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Sensitive” information is anything that could be used in malicious ways against Giving Jar or its employees (social security numbers, usernames/passwords, etc.). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to the Giving Jar Blog!</title>
        <link>http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/welcome/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://givingjarblog.surge.sh/welcome/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hopefully you wandered onto this page to learn more about Giving Jar and how it will improve charitable giving online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good news, this blog is exactly the right place to learn such things!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-giving-jar&quot;&gt;What is Giving Jar?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving Jar is a platform that makes it convenient for individuals and communities to donate to the charity of their choice online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;discover&quot;&gt;Discover&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guidestar.org/NonprofitDirectory.aspx&quot; title=&quot;GuideStar Nonprofit Directory&quot;&gt;GuideStar&lt;/a&gt;, one of the largest nonprofit databases in the world, there are over 1.8 million charitable organizations in the United States alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With so many charities to consider, finding the one that matches your own ideals can be challenging and time-consuming. From a nonprofit’s perspective, trying to spread the word about your mission when there are so many other charities… well, it can be difficult to be heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving Jar wants to help charities be discovered so it is easy for people to donate to organizations that match their passions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog is just one example. If you’re interested in learning about unsung nonprofits, come back occasionally and catch up on the charity spotlights. Better yet, if you sign up for the &lt;a href=&quot;//givingjar.org&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar&quot;&gt;Giving Jar newsletter&lt;/a&gt; you can read the spotlights before they are posted to this blog!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;decide&quot;&gt;Decide&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year Giving Jar sent a survey to 110 individuals online all over the country. The result was clear: 86% of those surveyed want to be able to choose the charity that receives their donations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even without those survey results, it is important to Giving Jar that anyone using it should be able to choose where their donations go. Giving Jar helps you find the right charity and then makes sure you can donate to them when you’re ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;donate&quot;&gt;Donate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final goal of Giving Jar is to offer a consistent way for you to donate. Suppose you want to give to five different organizations. Instead of visiting five different websites, you can go to &lt;a href=&quot;//givingjar.org&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar&quot;&gt;Giving Jar&lt;/a&gt; and donate to all five from one place. Or even better yet, why go anywhere? What if Giving Jar could come to you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving Jar would like to become a platform where donors don’t have to go out of their way to visit Giving Jar to make donations. Wouldn’t it be nice if you could just go about your business and opportunities to donate would instead present themselves to you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-will-giving-jar-improve-charitable-giving-online&quot;&gt;How Will Giving Jar Improve Charitable Giving Online?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s fairly common to be presented with opportunities to donate when we’re not online. Nonprofits host fundraisers in high traffic public places all the time, employers sponsor and support charitable events and allow donations to be made right out of your paycheck, and some businesses offer customers the opportunity to donate their spare change when making a purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ways to donate are great because they remove the burden of proactive donation from the donor. Those techniques are tough to emulate online, though. Someone with the correct technical knowhow has to build them before they are even possible. Think about it this way: you can’t take your kids and setup a table to ask for donations at your favorite online store unless someone with years of experience writes software that lets you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking the burden off of the online donor is difficult, but it is possible. Giving Jar wants to write that software for you and for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-to-begin&quot;&gt;Where to Begin?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving Jar is being built as a platform for discovering charities, deciding where you want to give, and making donations without having to go out of your way to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually this platform will allow anyone to easily build upon it and offer new ways to encourage charitable giving. That’s a lot of software to build, though, and Giving Jar doesn’t want to hold up new ways to donate any longer than is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the platform will be built piece by piece. This puts value in the hands of donors as early as possible and helps Giving Jar create a stable foundation to its donation platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;get-involved&quot;&gt;Get Involved!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Giving Jar sounds interesting to you, there are many ways you can support it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way is to subscribe to the &lt;a href=&quot;//givingjar.org&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar&quot;&gt;Giving Jar newsletter&lt;/a&gt;. When you subscribe, you will get previews of upcoming content such as charity spotlights and the occasional opportunity to provide feedback about what you would like to see in Giving Jar. Don’t worry, we don’t send a large number of emails, we won’t give away your email address, and you can unsubscribe whenever you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other ways to follow Giving Jar’s progress too. Follow Giving Jar on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/givingjar&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar on Twitter&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/givingjarorg&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar on Facebook&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, add our &lt;a href=&quot;//blog.givingjar.org/feed.xml&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar Blog RSS Feed&quot;&gt;RSS feed&lt;/a&gt; to your favorite reader, or come back and read the &lt;a href=&quot;//blog.givingjar.org&quot; title=&quot;Giving Jar Blog&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; once in awhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you really like what you see, tell a friend!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
